<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="editing_the_file">
  <title>Editing the file</title>

  <para>...</para>

  <section>
    <title>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Compare from current offset</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command</title>

    <para>If you need to compare two files then load one into Frhed and choose this
    command. You will first be prompted to choose the file to compare with.
    Choose a file and then the OK button. Comparison will occur from the current caret offset.</para>

    <para>If the chosen file matches the data in the loaded file from the current offset, you will
    be prompted so. Otherwise you will get a list of areas of difference to choose from. Areas
    of difference are ranges of bytes which are different in the files. For example:</para>

<screen>File 1: 00 01 02 03 04 (loaded file)
File 2: 00 ff ff 03 04</screen>

    <para>In this case you will  get one area of difference 2 bytes in size from offset 1 to 2.
    These offsets are measured relative to the current caret position. When you choose an area
    of difference then it will be selected and displayed in the main window.</para>

    <para>You can also copy the list of differences to the clipboard.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Get floating point value</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command</title>
    <para>This will show you the floating point values starting at the current caret position.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>File properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command</title>
    <para>Choose this to get the filename, path and size of the current file, and also the total number of lines of the hexdump.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Apply template</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command</title>

    <para>Use this command to apply a binary template on the file.
    A binary template consists of a text file with the extension
    "tpl" that contains a number of variable type+name combinations,
    such as this:</para>

<screen>BYTE filetype
WORD version
DWORD filelength</screen>

    <para>This sample template file named "sample.tpl" is included in the Frhed directory. When the command
    is chosen from the menu you will be prompted to choose the template file you want to apply. Frhed will
    then load that file and use the code in it to give you a structured "interpretation" of the data in the
    currently loaded file, starting at the current byte. The result will be displayed in the edit-box of a
    dialog, from where you can copy the result to the clipboard if necessary. The result looks like this:</para>

    <screen>File: C:\Data\test.dat
Template file: C:\frhed\sample.tpl
Applied at offset: 15

BYTE filetype = 66 (signed) = 66 (unsigned) = 0x42 = 'B'
WORD version = 30285 (signed) = 30285 (unsigned) = 0x764d
DWORD filelength = 8 (signed) = 8 (unsigned) = 0x8

-&gt; Length of template = 7 bytes.</screen>

    <para>Following variable types are recognized: (recognition is case-sensitive, so "byte" is not recognized as type "BYTE")</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>a byte-size value: &quot;BYTE&quot;, &quot;char&quot;</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>a word-size value: &quot;WORD&quot;, &quot;short&quot;</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>a longword-size value: &quot;DWORD&quot;, &quot;int&quot;, &quot;long&quot;, &quot;LONG&quot;</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>a float value: &quot;float&quot;</simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>a double value: &quot;double&quot;</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Open in text editor</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command</title>
    <para>This function attempts to call an external text editing program with the current file as argument.
    You have the option of saving the file first. The default editor is the Windows Notepad. You can
    choose the editor in the <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>View Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog.</para>
  </section>
</article>