<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>How do I search for hex values?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>You have to describe the values using a special syntax (as described in
        "Using the special syntax" in the help file). For example the byte value 0xf7
        has to be written as (you must write the angled brackets too!)</para>

        <screen>&lt;bh:f7&gt;</screen>

        <para>where the b means byte-sized value (otherwise use a "w" for word-size or "l" for longword-size)
        and the h means hexadecimal notation (otherwise use "d" for decimal notation).
        This notation can be combined with text after it or before it, or several encoded values after
        another etc.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>Frhed opens all files from Explorer supenly. How do I remove this behavior?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>Uncheck the following: <menuchoice><guimenu>Registry</guimenu><guimenuitem>In all context menu</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>, <menuchoice><guimenu>Registry</guimenu><guimenuitem>Is default in unknown context</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
        &amp; <menuchoice><guimenu>Registry</guimenu><guimenuitem>In unknown context menu</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
        Or edit the registry - Delete HKCR\*\shell\Open in Frhed\,
        HKCR\Unknown\shell\Open in Frhed\ &amp; the "(Default)" values under their parent keys.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>What do the B:??, W:??, L:?? in the status bar mean?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>These show you the byte (B), word (W) and longword (L) value beginning at the current cursor
        position, interpreted as either signed or unsigned, which is indicated in front of the "B:".</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>I know that two files I am comparing with the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>Compare from current offset</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command are equal,
        why does Frhed show me lots of differences?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>As the command's name indicates, the file you choose from the following dialogue is compared
        to the currently loaded file beginning from the CURRENT CURSOR POSITION. So if you want to know
        if the two files match completely beginning to end, you must put the blinking cursor in the
        very first position of the file, that is, at index zero. Just press Ctrl+Pos1 on the keyboard to
        go there directly.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
        <para>My Wheel Mouse does not work correctly with Frhed. Are wheel mice supported?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>I also use a Logitech wheel mouse, which works fine with Frhed. It is possible that the standard
        drivers installed by Windows for wheel mice do things slightly differently than the "real" Logitech
        drivers. I suggest you install the original drivers supplied by your mouse manufacturer. If
        you have any success with this, please tell me about it, I don't know if this really works.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</article>