<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="file_operations">
  <title>File Operations</title>

  <section>
    <title>Creating new files</title>

    <para>If Frhed is started without parameters or with a nonexistant
    filename as parameter, then it starts with a new, empty file that is
    untitled. If a file is already loaded, then choose <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the menu. If a file is already loaded and it has been
    changed, then you will be prompted if you want to save the changes.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Opening files</title>

    <para>Files can be opened to Frhed in many ways. The most common way to
    open a file is to choose <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the menu. If a file is already loaded and it has been
    changed, then you will be prompted if you want to lose the changes, save
    the changes or cancel the request.</para>

    <para>A file can also be dragged (for instance from the Windows Explorer
    window) into Frhed's window to open it. If several files were dragged,
    then you must choose which one to open.</para>

    <para>Frhed remembers last opened files and shows them in File-menu's Most
    Recently Used -list (MRU). File can be opened by selecting it from the
    list.</para>

    <para>If the file access permissions don't allow writing or open-read-only
    mode is on then read-only mode will be engaged.</para>

    <para>See also Frhed <xref linkend="CommandLine" /> usage.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>If you put a link to frhed.exe into the "SendTo"-Folder in your
      Windows main directory then you can open any file from the Explorer with
      Frhed by choosing Frhed from the "Send To"-item in the file's context
      menu.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Opening files partially</title>

    <para>If you want to edit a very large file and it's not necessary to load
    all of it into memory, choose the <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Open partially</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command. First you will have to choose the file you want
    to open in a File-Open-dialog. Then you must enter the offset from which
    the file will be loaded and how many bytes to load, or you can check the
    "Open partially from end of file"-radiobutton if you want to load data
    from the end of the file. Also you may have Frhed display the offsets
    relative to the start of the file instead of relative to the start of the
    loaded block. Note, however, that so far the rest of the program uses
    offsets relative to start of the loaded block.</para>

    <para>Frhed will now be in partially-opened-mode, which means that
    whenever you choose the <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command, the data will be written back to the position
    they were loaded from. This mode is indicated by a letter "P" in the
    window title after the file name.</para>

    <para>If the file has been changed, then you will be prompted if you want
    to lose the changes, save the changes or cancel the request.</para>

    <para>You can also resize the block of data you loaded and the
    corresponding section of the file will also be resized when you save the
    file.</para>

    <para>If the file access permissions don't allow writing or open-read-only
    mode is on then read-only mode will be engaged.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Saving files</title>

    <para>To save the current file choose <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Save</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the menu. If the file has never been saved before,
    then <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Save as</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> will be automatically invoked.</para>

    <para><menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Save as</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> saves the file with a different name.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Saving selections</title>

    <para>To save the current selection choose <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Save selection as</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> from the menu. If the is no selection then all of the file
    will be saved.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reverting to the saved file</title>

    <para>When you have made changes to a file, want to change it back and
    cannot remember the exact bytes in the file then the <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command will do it for you. If the file has never been
    saved then this command will revert to an untitled empty file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Insert file</title>

    <para>The <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Insert file</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command inserts the requested file between the current
    byte and previous one, replacing the selection if there is any.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exporting the file as a hexdump text</title>

    <para>The <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Export as hexdump</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command is used if you need the hexdump of the file in
    plain text form, for example if you need to insert it in a word processor
    document. You can either put the hexdump into the clipboard or into a
    file, which you will have to choose. The start line of the hexdump has to
    be specified (in hexadecimal notation without prefix), which you can find
    on the left side of the window, for example 23c or 134. You must also
    specify the end line. The values in the dialog will be initialized so that
    the whole file will be dumped, if there is nothing selected, or they will
    be such that the current selection will be dumped.</para>

    <para>Also you have the option of just outputting the hex bytes on a
    single line - just uncheck the "Export like Frhed display" check
    box.</para>

    <para>Also you have the option of outputting an RTF hexdump of the lines.
    The RTF is output by Frhed as follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The file that was hexdumped in the document properties as the
        Title.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Times New Roman 20pt paragraph containing the file name of the
        file that was hexdumped.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Each line of hexdump, with the selection or current byte
        highlighted as per the display colours.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Bookmarks are both highlighted and put into the document. The
        bookmark name is that same as what you gave Frhed, unless you didn't
        give a name, in which case the name will be the offset of the bookmark
        in decimal. The document bookmarks will be in the same place as the
        caret.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The separators are put in a single group together and are simple
        lines as per the display settings.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limitations: the RTF output is not perfect in these ways:</para>

        <para>For the chars Microsoft Word will convert some into underscores
        (generally the control characters up to 0x20). This is only apparent
        in OEM mode since in ANSI mode Frhed translates these chars into
        periods (.).</para>

        <para>Microsoft Word will alter the bookmark names by replacing
        non-alphanumerics with underscores, place "BM" in front of bookmarks
        that begin with a number and hide bookmarks beginning with underscores
        (can still view them with "Hidden bookmarks" checked).</para>

        <para>If your display is running at anything less than 24 bit colour
        you may not get the colours you expect for the caret. This is because
        at lower bit levels the InvertRect function (which Frhed uses to
        invert the caret in the window) works differently than just inverting
        the bits of colours as it does at 24-bit &amp; as Frhed does in
        generating the inverted colour for RTF export. If someone finds out
        how InvertRect works at lower bit levels please let me (Pabs)
        know.</para>

        <para>The bookmarks border takes up space (at least on Word2000) which
        means that subsequent characters on the same line will be displaced to
        the right 2 pixels. This is noticable when there is a selection
        covering two adjacent lines, one with &amp; one without a bookmark.
        There is little that can be done about this except try a different
        word processor.</para>

        <para>The separators will not always be sized or positioned exactly.
        There is not much that can be done about this since it is hard to know
        the exact size in twips the word processor will display the text at.
        An alternative to this might be to use tables, which might not work
        and might also solve the bookmark problem.</para>

        <para>At some fonts &amp; sizes (esp. OEM &amp; ANSI 9, ANSI 10) Frhed
        cannot determine the correct font name the system chose &amp; this
        will cause Word to use the wrong font, often this will be Times New
        Roman. This may or may not be true depending on whether or not the
        font mapper for your system uses one font for all sizes and the fonts
        you have installed. Unfortunately Word ignores the other font hints
        that can be determined; character set, variable/monospaced and font
        family.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deleting the current file</title>

    <para>The <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Delete File</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command deletes the file currently opened in the editor
    and closes it. This requires a double confirmation because it could be
    disastrous.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>USE WITH CAUTION! When ever you edit files using any hex editor
      you should <emphasis role="bold">always</emphasis> have a backup
      anyway.</para>
    </warning>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Importing a hexdump file</title>

    <para>The <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>File</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Import from hexdump</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> command imports hexdump data from the clipboard or from a
    file.</para>

    <para>The data you choose to import can be in one of two formats. One is a
    text version of the display &amp; the other is all the hex digits on one
    line.</para>

    <para>The Frhed will try to determine the type by looking for characters
    that are not whitespace or hexdigits and you will be asked to verify the
    Frhed's findings.</para>

    <para>If you decide it is in the Frhed display format then you will be
    asked if you want the display settings found in the file to replace
    current ones. If so, Frhed can determine the offset length, the number of
    bytes per line, if the offset length should be automatically adjusted and
    possibly if the data is ANSI/OEM from its contents. If any of these cannot
    be determined their settings will remain the same.</para>

    <para>Frhed will also notify you if the character and hex data do not
    agree with each other or the offsets are invalid and you may choose to
    ignore any more of these notices.</para>

    <para>If illegal characters are found in the hexdata section or the data
    ends unexpectedly the operation will not be able to continue and you will
    have the option of keeping the data that has already been found or
    cancelling the operation.</para>

    <para>Also if the first offset found is not zero you can insert that
    amount of null bytes at the start of the file and if you choose not to and
    you chose to alter relevant display settings then Frhed will display
    offsets relative to the first offset found.</para>

    <para>If you decide it is not in the Frhed display format then Frhed will
    go through the file filtering out whitespace and adding each hex digit
    found as a nibble (If odd no's of hex digits are present then '0' will be
    the last nibble). If other characters are found Frhed will complain and
    give you the option of ignoring the any other illegal characters that are
    found.</para>

    <para>If the file access permissions don't allow writing or open-read-only
    mode is on then read-only mode will be engaged.</para>

    <para>If the current file has been changed, then you will be prompted if
    you want to lose the changes, save the changes or cancel the
    request.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>If the file was output using an offset length that is smaller than
      is required the parser will determine that the character data does not
      match the hex data. If the output data is edited to the same as with an
      offset length of 2 the same thing happens. This occurs because of a bug
      in <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>File</guimenu>

          <guimenuitem>Export as Hexdump</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>, causing it to remove characters from the end of each
      line that has larger offset lengths than that of the first line. This
      bug was fixed in v1.0.156.Pabs. If you know the file was output using a
      small offset length and are sure that you have not edited it press Yes
      to ignore any further mismatches, no to ignore that one or cancel to
      cancel the Import operation. Ignoring the mismatches will have no
      effect.</para>
    </warning>
  </section>
</article>