<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="Locales">
  <title id="LocaleSupport">Locale support</title>

  <simpara>Frhed user interface is in English by default. But the language can
  be changed to other languages for which translations have been contributed.
  Localization affects all visible texts in the user interface.</simpara>

  <section>
    <title>Installing localizations</title>

    <para>Localizations are installed by selecting them in the installer. If
    some localization is missing you can run the installer again and select
    it.</para>

    <para>Localizations can be also installed and updated by copying translation
    files to the <filename class="directory">Languages</filename>-subfolder in
    Frhed installation folder. All translation files have filename of
    <filename>[langcode].po</filename>. For example <filename>de.po</filename>
    for German translation file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Selecting the Frhed interface language</title>

    <para>Interface language can be selected from the <guilabel>View
    settings</guilabel> -dialog which is found from
    <guimenu>Options</guimenu>-menu. In bottom of the dialog there is a dropdown
    control which contains all installed translations. The language can be
    changed by opening the dropdown and selecting the language from the
    list.</para>

    <para>After the language selection the interface language is changed. There
    is no need to re-start Frhed.</para>

    <para>If the wanted language is not shown in the list it is not installed or
    simply not yet contributed. Check the latest installer if there are more
    languages available.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Available localizations</title>

    <para>Frhed localizations currently contributed and available are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Dutch</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>French</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>German</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reporting errors in translation</title>

    <para>If you see an error in translation, please submit a bug report to our
    <ulink
    url="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=236485&amp;atid=1100163">bug
    tracker</ulink>. It would be great if you can provide or suggest a fix. It
    is also possible to discuss about translations in our <ulink
    url="???">discussion forums</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Submitting a new translation</title>

    <para>If you want to help us and translate Frhed to new language (not yet in
    above list) you should first read our translation documentation. The
    documentation is available:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>via <ulink
          url="http://frhed.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/frhed/trunk/Docs/Developers/Translations.html">ViewVC
          from version control</ulink></simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>downloading the latest source package and opening the document
          <filename>Docs/Developers/Translations.html</filename></simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>PO files used to translate Frhed do not require any special tools. But
    it is recommended to use tools described in the above mentioned
    document.</para>
  </section>
</article>