<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="main_window">
  <title>Main Window</title>

  <para>The window's title shows the name of the currently loaded file in square brackets,
  with an asterisk on it's right side if the file has been changed. If a file is loaded,
  you will find something like this in the window's client area:</para>

<screen>000000  23 42 34 53 56 45 76 45  #B4SVEvE
000008  64 56 0a bc 0a 35 c0 08  dV...5..
000010  06 be 09 07 bb 07 00 00  ........
000018  00 00 00 00 00 00 07 __  .......</screen>

  <para>On the far left are the offsets of the first byte in the line in hexadecimal notation.
  You can choose the offset length or make it automatically adjusted to the length of the
  largest offset with the <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>View Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command or right-click the offsets to
  increment their lengths or left-click them to decrement their lengths (when auto-adjust is off).
  Then come the actual byte values, with vertical separating lines after every fourth byte in the line.
  You can choose the number of bytes to display per line with <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>View Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice>,
  and also, if it should be automatically adjusted to the window width. To the far right
  are the character representations of these values, with dotted lines on the left and
  right of this section. You can choose the character set for these representations as
  well as the font size with the <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>Character set</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command. As you can see, the
  first byte of the second line of the sample hexdump has the hexadecimal value 64
  and the corresponding character is a lower case "d". The position after the last
  byte of the file is marked with a double underscore "__" in the byte section.</para>

  <para>Blinking in the window somewhere is a rectangular caret, if the window is enabled.
  If it is in the byte section, then it stands on either of the two nibbles (half-bytes).
  If it is in the character section, then it stands on one character corresponding with
  one byte. In either case the corresponding other representation is shown inverted in 
  the other section.</para>

  <para>On the bottom of the window is the status bar, which displays additional information.
  In the first section of the status bar you can find the current offset of the byte
  which the caret is marking in hexadecimal and decimal notation. After that come the
  bits of the current byte. Also in this section, on the right side, is something like this:</para>

<screen>Unsigned: B:35,W:16931,L:1395933731</screen>

  <para>These are the values of the byte (B:), the word (W:) and the longword (L:) value starting
  at this offset in decimal notation. These are computed depending on the setting for signed or
  unsigned values (Choose with the <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>View Settings</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command) and on the binary mode setting,
  either Little-endian (Intel format) or Big-endian (Motorola format).
  Choose with the <menuchoice><guimenu>Options</guimenu><guimenuitem>Binary mode</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command.</para>

  <para>In the second section of the status bar are indicators for:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>character set: &quot;ANSI&quot; or &quot;OEM&quot;.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>entering mode: &quot;OVR&quot; for overwriting or &quot;INS&quot; for inserting on keyboard input. If Frhed is in read-only mode, then there will be a &quot;READ&quot; here.</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <simpara>binary mode: &quot;L&quot; for Little-endian or &quot;B&quot; for Big-endian.</simpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In the third section the file size in bytes is displayed.</para>

  <para>The status bar can also be used to toggle various parameters
  and act as a shortcut to certain commands.</para>

  <para>The status bar takes into account the same factors when considering
  if the selected command should be carried out as the menus do when
  disabling commands. If there are 2 alternatives in one place and
  one is disabled then the other one will be used.</para>

  <para>A single left click in the third section is a shortcut to <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
  (right is <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>File properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>) - Note that this may change in the future.</para>

  <para>Clicking in the middle section will toggle the parameter clicked on
  - ANSI &harr; OEM, READ &rarr; INS &rarr; OVR &rarr; READ&hellip; (right-click
   goes back other way) , L &harr; B.</para>

  <para>Left or right clicking in the first section can result in many different
  things depending on where you click and state of the file opened.</para>

  <para>When part of the file is selected you may deselect (cursor goes to the
  first nibble of the first byte of the selection or last of last for a
  right click) by clicking in the space on the right or the word "Selected:"
  or alter the selection using <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Select block</guimenuitem></menuchoice> by clicking in the offsets region.</para>

  <para>If the file is empty clicking the first part will bring up <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Append</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>

  <para>If the file is not empty and the cursor is on the end byte then <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Goto</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
  will be activated on a left click or the cursor goes to the previous byte
  on a right click.</para>

  <para>Otherwise (when not on the end byte, selected or empty) the click behaviour
  is complex and summarised in the table below. The right action is
  omitted where it is the same as the left one.</para>

  <informaltable frame="none">
    <tgroup cols="7">
      <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="14*"/>
      <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="14*"/>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <para>Text</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Offset 0=0x0</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>  Bits=</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>00100011</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>                   </para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Unsigned:</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>B:35,W:8227,L:1766662179</para>
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <para>Area</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Offset</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Bits</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Actual bits</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Space</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Un/signed</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>B, W &amp; L values</para>
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <para>Left</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Goto</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Bit manip dlg</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Direct bit manip</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Select block</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Toggle un/signed</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Enter decimal value with the size set to the one clicked in</para>
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <para>Right</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>View settings</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para/>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para/>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para>Goto</para>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para/>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <para/>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>

  <para>If you have suggestions as to what else the status bar could/should (not) do just
  drop me (<ulink url="mailto:pabs3@zip.to">Pabs</ulink>) a line.</para>

  <para>The window also has a vertical and a horizontal scrollbar, which can be used to
  scroll the view. They don't change the caret position.</para>
</article>