<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="moving_in_the_file">
  <title>Moving in the file</title>

  <para>You can move the caret with the arrow keys. Press TAB to toggle the editing mode between byte and
  character editing. When there is a selection TAB brings the selection into the middle of the display.</para>

  <para>You can also jump to any position by choosing the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Go To</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command and entering
  an offset, like "125", which will set the caret position to offset 125 decimal. For relative jumps
  in the file, for example if you want to go to an offset 150 bytes after the current one, you have
  to start with "+" as the first character and follow this with either a decimal number or a hex
  number starting with "x". So to jump 150 bytes forward you have to enter "+150" or "+x96" in hex
  notation. For backward relative jumps start with "-" (minus) as the first character.</para>

  <para>To jump to the start of the line press Home or End for the end of the line.
  To jump directly to the end of the file press Ctrl+End, for the beginning Ctrl+Home.</para>

  <para>Frhed can find text and binary values in a file. Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to do this.
  In the dialog you can choose if the case of the text parts of the find string are to be
  ignored and the find direction. To encode binary values, Frhed uses a special syntax. Example:</para>

  <screen>Here is the findstring&lt;bd:0&gt;FloatValue&lt;fl:-14.56&gt;</screen>

  <para>This will cause Frhed to search for a string "Here is the findstring." followed by a
  zero-byte, then the text "FloatValue" and a 4-byte float with the value -14.56.</para>

  <para>Note that coded binary values will also be transformed by the "match case" option of the Find
  command, so if you search for a byte with the hex value of 0x41 (this is the upper-case letter "A")
  with the match-case option disabled, then Frhed will also find bytes with the hex value 0x61
  (the lower-case letter "a"). Therefore you should always search for discrete binary values with
  case-matching enabled or you might not get correct results.
  Please see <xref linkend="special_syntax" /> for further information.</para>

  <para>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find next</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find previous</guimenuitem></menuchoice> commands find the next or previous
  occurance of the findstring last entered in the Find-dialog, with the match-case option enabled
  or disabled as chosen in it. If there was no previous findstring the both Find next &amp; Find previous
  commands will bring up the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Find</guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog.</para>

  <para>By positioning the mouse cursor on a byte or a character and pressing the left mouse
  button you can also set the caret position.</para>

  <para>You can also move in the file by choosing one of the bookmarks in the <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu>
  menu section. The caret will be set to that offset immediately.</para>
</article>