<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="registry_menu">
  <title>The <guimenu>Registry</guimenu> Menu</title>

  <para>The <guimenu>Registry</guimenu> menu contains items related to methods
  of launching Frhed, the registry data, relations with previous versions of
  Frhed and different instances of Frhed.</para>

  <para>Of course if you are a power user you will probably prefer to do all
  of the below yourself.</para>

  <section>
    <title>In all context menu</title>

    <para>When checked this item indicates that in the context menu of all
    files there appears an item named <guimenuitem>Open in Frhed</guimenuitem>
    which will launch Frhed with the file opened.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>In unknown context menu</title>

    <para>The same is true of this item except that the item appears only in
    the context menu of files that have an extension that has not yet been
    registered with Windows. NOTE that if both are checked both will appear on
    the menu of unregistered files and that these files generally have an
    <guimenuitem>Open with…</guimenuitem> command.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Is default in unknown context</title>

    <para>When this item is checked the "Open in Frhed" command for
    unregistered files becomes the default action when double clicking or
    pressing enter on these files in explorer. This may not work properly but
    it should. The reason a similar option was not provided for the all
    context is that then you would not be able to open your files with the
    proper applications. It is not recommended but if you wish you may do this
    yourself - just set the default value in the key
    "HKEY_CLASSES_ROOT\*\shell" to "<guimenuitem>Open in Frhed</guimenuitem>.
    This is disabled if the above option is not checked. Unchecking the above
    option unchecks and disables this one.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Save ini when required</title>

    <para>When this item is unchecked Frhed will not save data to the registry
    when it normally does. It does this on exit and at other times - see the
    source where the function save_ini_data is called. This option was added
    so that the <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Registry</guimenu>

        <guimenuitem>Remove Frhed</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice> item could work properly.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Change instance</title>

    <para>Allows the user to switch from one set of instance options to
    another and to specify the instance number to save to on exit and at other
    times. Note that if 2 or more instances of Frhed are open at once the
    options you save on exit may be overwritten. If you enter a non-existent
    instance number that instance will be written to the registry with current
    values and current values will stay the same. This option is always
    enabled so that you may reload instance options at any time.</para>
  </section>

</article>